CAIO C. VELASCO

+34 611 85 03 96 caiocvelasco@gmail.com

Brazilian engineer who holds a Master's degree in Economics and Public Policy from UCLA, with a full scholarship from the Lemann Foundation and the General Electric Foundation for academic excellence. Experience ranges from Advanced Math and Statistics, Causal Inference, Business Analysis, Product Ownership, Analytics Engineering, and Consulting. I live in Barcelona and I'm available for Autónomo/Contractor/Freelancer.

Tech stack: Git/Github, Docker, AWS, Snowflake, SQL, Python, dbt, Airflow, Power BI.

EDUCATION

TILBURG UNIVERSITY Tilburg, Netherlands

PhD in Economics (unfinished)

August 2020 - December 2021

- Top 5 European Economics Department. Main topics: Advanced Math, Statistics, Microeconomics, Causal Inference.
- Due to family issues in Brazil during the Covid-19 pandemic, I quit the PhD and transitioned to data science.

UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA LOS ANGELES - UCLA

Los Angeles, USA

Master of Economics and Public Policy

August 2017 - June 2019

- Top 15 university worldwide (The Times Higher Education World University Rankings).
- Main topics: Econometrics, Microeconomics. Awarded a full scholarship from the Lemann Foundation.

FEDERAL UNIVERSITY OF RIO DE JANEIRO - UFRJ

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

December 2012

- Top 8 Latin American university (QS Latin America University Rankings 2023).
- Highest grade award in the class of 2012 of 100+ students.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

IAG - INTERNATIONAL AIRLINE GROUP

London, UK

Freelancer Data Engineer (Remote Job, 4-month contract opportunity)

January 2024 – April 2024

- Designed end-to-end ETL processes from CSV to PowerBI with Git, AWS, dbt, Snowflake, Python, SQL.
- Ad hoc data analysis and helped migrate SQL code into dbt models.

BLUE ORANGE DIGITAL, A.I. & DATA ANALYTICS CONSULTING

New York, USA

Product Owner & Analytics Engineer (Remote Job, Self-Employed)

May 2022 – December 2023

- Led the development of customizable reporting tools (control panels, dashboards, reports).
- Managed multiple stakeholders (Data Engineers, Back/Frontend Developers, Product Designers).
- Improved data quality and migrated legacy SQL code into dbt models for a Unified Data Model.

ROYAL HOLLOWAY UNIVERSITY OF LONDON

Egham, England

Pre-Doctoral Assistant to Professor Juan Pablo Rud (Remote Job, Self-Employed)

November 2019 – Abril 2020

 Econometric analysis with STATA and Python (numpy, pandas) for a World Bank research project about the relationship between climate change and agricultural productivity in African countries.

UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA LOS ANGELES

Los Angeles, USA

Research Assistant to Professor Adriana Lleras-Muney

September 2018 – July 2019

Econometric analysis with STATA for a project on the relationship between family planning and access to welfare.

MEPREPARA, ONLINE DIGITAL PRODUCT

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Founder

May 2016 - Present

• Designed a fully automated math course to prepare low-income Brazilians for the mathematics part of GRE / GMAT exams, required at prestigious MBA and PhD programs worldwide.

AOG EDUCATION CONSULTING

São José dos Campos, Brazil

Senior Consultant

January 2015 – December 2015

• Examined two large private schools' operations in two different states in Brazil. Mapped processes on the staffing structure, budget preparation, enrollment procedures. Developed a plan of action for improvements.

Entrepreneur in Residence

December 2012 - December 2014

• Stone is a Brazilian FinTech unicorn startup. I was its first employee, reporting directly to the founders. I designed the first draft of Stone's credit card reconciliation process, which included authorization, settlement, chargeback, adjustments, and receivables. Worked with multiple stakeholders (product, engineering, finance).

AWARDS

KOOPMANS SCHOLARSHIP, TILBURG UNIVERSITY, NETHERLANDS, 2020

Awarded the Koopmans Scholarship for academic excellence.

LEMANN FOUNDATION SCHOLARSHIP, UCLA, USA, 2017

 Top young professionals from Brazil with academic excellence who were accepted for a master program at Harvard, Stanford, MIT, Columbia, UCLA, or Oxford.

GLOBAL PRE-MBA LEADERSHIP PROGRAM, YALE UNIVERSITY, USA, 2013

Top 60 young people all over the world selected to explore MBA education, sponsored by Goldman Sachs.

CHANGE COURSE CONFERENCE, THE CLUB OF ROME, SWITZERLAND, 2012

Top 60 young people all over the world selected to explore MBA education.

MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, FEDERAL UNIVERSITY OF RIO DE JANEIRO, 2012

Awarded the highest recognition due to the highest grade among all mechanical engineering students.

BRAZILIAN GOVERNMENT & USA DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION, 2011

Full Scholarship for the best engineering students to study engineering at North Carolina State University in the USA.

GENERAL ELECTRIC SCHOLAR-LEADER PROGRAM, BRAZIL, 2010

• Global scholarship awarded to the top 10 Brazilian engineering students with both leadership and social skills.

SKILLS

- Technical:
 - Tech Stack: Git, GitHub, ETL, SQL, Python, dbt, AWS, Snowflake, Power BI/Tableau, Microsoft Office.
 - o GitHub Portfolio
 - o Currently learning Docker, DuckDB & Airflow.
- Languages: Portuguese (Native), English (Fluent), Spanish (Intermediate).